Guide to the Barbara Bergmann Papers, 1942-2015 RL.11388
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Project Files, 1972-2013; 2
  - Marriage research files, 2010s; 16 folders (Box 7)
    Clippings, collected subject files re: marriage, single parenting, divorce, cohabitation, political attitudes toward marriage. Presumably compiled for Bergmann's Decline of Marriage book (chapter 1 draft is in the Writing Series under Books).
  - Nursing shortages/SEIU/antitrust lawsuits, etc., 1990s-2000s; 6 folders (Box 7)
    Files collected by Bergmann documenting class-action lawsuits by nurses against hospitals accused of collusion in order to keep nurse wages low and non-competitive. Includes materials from Bergmann's role as a consultant for the SEIU and her research/interviews/subpoenas regarding some of the lawsuits.
  - Wetzel vs. Liberty Mutual amicus brief material, undated (Box 7)
    Incomplete draft/research regarding pregnant women's insurance disability claims.
- Autobiographical/Personal Materials, 1980s-2015; 3
  - Bergmann's Cornell University B.A. diploma, 1948 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Photographs of Bergmann: headshots, 1980s-2010s (Box 7)
  - Draft statement: Barbara R. Bergmann, 1986 Jan. 27 (Box 7)
    Typed statement detailing the gender discrimination Bergmann faced at the University of Maryland Economics Department, including personal treatment and salary inequity.
  - Profile of Bergmann in Footnotes, AAUP newsletter, 1990 (Box 7)
  - American Association of University Professors award collage, 1992 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - NewsTalk Television: Afternoon Edition Segment videotape, 1996 May 15; 1 VHS (Box 5)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
    "BRB talk show"
  - Bill Moyers/Sports for Sale interview, undated; 2 VHS (Box 5)
  - "This one's for you, Barbara," honorary Feminist Economics issue, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Collegium Muhlenbergiense honorary degree, 2000 (Box 7)
  - Barbara Berman Bergmann chapter in Engendering Economics, 2002 (Box 7)
    Interview with Bergmann.
  - "A Tribute to Barbara Bergmann in her 75th Year", 2003 Jan. 3; 2 items 1 VHS, 1 DVD (Box 5)
    Video recordings from program held during Allied Social Science Association's Annual Convention.
  - Carolyn Shaw Bell award plaque, 2004 (Box 8)
  - Distinguished Service award from Eastern Economic Association plaque, 2004 (Box 8)
  - American Academy of Political and Social Science fellowship (ceremony), 2006 (Box 8)
  - "We have to turn the world into Sweden" profile/interview, Intervention, 2009 (Box 8)
  - Brief biography, 2000s (Box 8)
  - Autobiographical essay/draft, 2009 (Box 8)
  - Remembering Barbara Bergmann: IAFFE memorial booklet, writings by/about Bergmann, 2015 (Box 8)
    Dedicated to Bergmann's daughter, Sarah, with memories contributed by members of IAFFE
- Teaching, 1982-2010; 4
  - Calendar/schedule, 1982-1995; 3 folders (Box 8)
  - American University employment/hiring, 1987-1989 (Box 8)
  - Sex Roles in Economic Life course packets, 1994 and undated (Box 8)
  - American University Economics Dept. miscellaneous materials, 1990s-2007 (Box 8)
  - American University tribute, 2010 (Box 8)
- Research Files/Bergmann's Library, 1942-2006; 5
  - A short table of integrals, by B.O. Pierce, 1942 (Box 8)
    Includes Bergmann's inscription, "And Barbara Berman, late inmate of Cascadilla Hall."
  - Photocopy of American Foot Binding poster (featuring high heel shoes), Rochester Women Against Violence Against Women, 1980 (Box 8)
  - Poverty and income trends: 1994, by R. May and K. Porter, 1996 Mar. (Box 8)
  - "The family" in public policy: fallacious assumptions and gender implications, by Bina Aagarwell, 2000 (Box 8)
  - Cut loose: mostly older women talk about the end of (mostly) long term relationships, 2006 (Box 8)
    A draft review by Bergmann of this work is in the Book Reviews file, in the Writings Series.
  - Women's wages and work in the twentieth century, by J. Smith and M. Ward, 1984 Oct. (Box 8)
  - U.S. Census Bureau reports, statistics, and publications, 1976-2012; 12 folders (Box 8)
    Government reports on topics including poverty, income, marital status, women's work and wages, household economics, insurance coverage, etc.
  - College sports, inc.: the athletic department versus the university, by M. Sperber, 1990 (Box 9)
  - Patterns of dominance, by P. Mason, 1970 (Box 9)
  - Congress of the U.S. Congressional Budget Office: Reducing poverty among children, 1985 May (Box 9)
  - Gender advertisements, by Erving Goffman, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Social security: the phony crisis, by D. Baker and M. Weisbrot, 1999 (Box 9)
  - The logic of collective action: public goods and the theory of groups, by M. Olson, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Mathematical theory of epidemics, by N.T.J. Bailey, 1957 (Box 9)
  - What's wrong with economics? By Ben Ward, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Poker for fun and profit, by I. Steig, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Computerization of micro-founded macro econometric models, by G. Holm-Petersen, 1978 (Box 9)
  - The feminine economy and economic man, by S. Burggraf, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Measuring poverty: a new approach, National Research Council, 1995 (Box 9)
  - Poverty and inequality: the political economy of redistribution, ed. by Jon Neill, 1997 (Box 9)
  - Engendering America: a documentary history 1865-present, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Analyzing gender: a handbook of social science research, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Ulysses and the Sirens: studies in rationality and irrationality, by J. Elster, 1979 (Box 9)
  - A journey through economic time, by J. K. Galbraith, 1994 (Box 9)
  - Econometrics, by R. and Th. Wonnacott, 1970 (Box 9)
  - The vices of economists, the virtues of the bourgeoisie, by D. McCluskey, 1996 (Box 9)
  - Stories employers tell: race, skill, and hiring in America, 2001 (Box 9)
  - The price of school readiness: a tool for estimating the cost of universal preschool in the United States, 2004 (Box 9)
  - Women's figures: the economic progress of women in America, by D. Furchtgott-Roth and C. Stolba, 1996 (Box 9)
  - Countdown to reform: the great Social Security debate, by H. Aaron and R. Reischauer, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Learning from the field: a guide from experience, by W. F. Whyte, 1984 (Box 9)
  - The shape of the river: longterm consequences of considering race in college and university admissions, by W. Bowen and D. Bok, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Conference proceedings for Women's Progress: 5th Women's Policy Research conference, 1998 (Box 9)